I built a simple computer and wrote a program to print hello world on the screen
But the program is a bit of mess right now
It's over 150 lines of assembly language just to print hello world
and see printing character by character here...you know it's very repetitive
because I just copy and pasted the code to print each character over and over again
and then if we go all the way back up to the top. I am doing the same thing at the top here just to
sent the instruction to get the display module set up in the first place
so let's simplify this by moving this code here for sending an instruction into a subroutine that we could just call with a single line of code each time we need to
so I'm gonna copy all of this and paste it way down here at the bottom of the program so this is all the way at the bottom and I will paste the same code
and I will add a label here called lcd_instruction and expect I'll spell it right
and I'm calling a Lcd instruction because this is the code that sends an instruction or whatever instruction in A register to the LCD module
so back up to the top here
here we're sending some instructions and we're loading the instruction into the A register and then
instead of having all these code here we just say jsr, which has jumped to subroutine, LCD instruction
so this will load the instruction into the A register and then jump down to the bottom here to this LCD instruction section here
and execute all this code here which actually sends that instruction to the LCD
then at the end of this we can say RTS, which means return from subroutine
which will exit the subroutine and then jump back up wherever we came from, so if we go back to the top here
that will jump here to where we just finish this jump subroutine instruction
and the nice thing is that we can reuse that subroutine for each of the instructions we need to configure the LCD
so instead of doing all this we get rid of that and say jsr lcd instruction
and the same thing here this is another instruction we get rid of all that and add another jump to subroutine LCD instruction
It's now... easier to follow this code because, here you know this is all the code to initialize the LCD module
and you can check out my last video where I go into what each of these instructions do and what each of these bits are for
but if you watched that video and know what these bits mean then hopefully this code is pretty clear about what it's doing
and of course you know I've also got the comments over here which should help assuming they're correct
and of course we can do the same thing for actually printing the letters
so all of this code here prints the letter H from the A register
so I am copying all that down into a subroutine down here at the bottom as well
and I can call that "print_character"
and it's pretty similar to the subroutine for the LCD instruction just we've got this register select bit set here
but again at the end we need the return from subroutine instruction to exit the subroutine and go back up to the main program
and so now we go back up here
we could replace all of this with just a "jump to subroutine print character"
and I'll go ahead and do that for each letter in the entire message
you can see this is gonna significantly reduce the amount of code we need to send each letter since most of the code we start with
was just repeating those same command to sent a letter to the display and now that's been factored out into that subroutine
and now this is what we left with and it's a lot shorter
and also I think a lot more clear of what it does
and a thing with assembly language there is a direct core relation with machine code it runs
so let's save this
if we look at machine code we starting with